It's crazy to say out loud, but we've been with
each other for 17 years now. Naturally,
we've had plenty of discussions on the topic
of children. Do we want to be parents? Is life
better without kids? Would there be any regret
if we didn't have children? Looking at our life
through social media, it might be easy to
assume we are DINKs (Dual income,
no kids). We have even been asked to do
interviews about being DINKs. But to the
many family planning questions we have gotten over
the years, we have always said maybe someday we
will have kids. Then life happened. Before we knew
it, we have already crossed into what's medically
considered advanced maternal age. Suddenly,
looking at the trajectory of our lives, it seems
like we will remain as DINKs after all, and we
were genuinely fine with that. To be child-free or
have children, both seemed like perfectly valid
choices, each with their own advantages. But
as usual on the internet, the discourse
between the child-free and pro-parenthood camps is
much more polarized. Agree or disagree? Choosing
not to have children is fundamentally selfish.
First of all, I think people tend to conflate
selfishness and self-interest. So in that sense,
if we use the terms loosely, then I would actually
agree because I believe outside of exceptional
cases when normal people like you and I when
we decide whether or not we want to have kids
is almost always from a self-interested point
of view. Our decision can be ultimately summed
up with one question. Do we want a life with
children or do we want a life without children?
And we acknowledge that either of those options
would be out of self-interest. It's based on what
we want. And we won't pretend we are doing it for
some selfless reason. So if somebody says, "Oh,
I actually really want kids. I just choose not
to to save the environment." Or "Oh, I don't even
want kids. I'm just doing it for the economy."
Personally, I'll be very skeptical.
Maybe altruistic reasons can play a minor role in
influencing a person's decisions to have kids or
not, but to me those have always sounded more like
retrospective rationalizations or justifications
for a personal decision that was much more
influenced by selfish decisions. But
because the choice of being child-free or to have
children is such a personal topic, accusations
start getting thrown around. You're selfish for
not having children. No, you are the one who's
selfish for having children. Guys, it's simple.
You're all selfish. We are all selfish, and that's
okay. It's unethical to bring children
into the world given the current state it's in.
That's just kind of a pessimistic way to look
at it, right? I mean, our grandparents went
through world wars, so surely the world wasn't
in a better state back then, but they had kids,
and that's why we're here today.
And I wouldn't say that they were being
unethical or irresponsible. Of course, there's
a lot of s*** going on in the world all the time,
but I think most of us would still agree that
life is overall still worth living. I
also feel like whatever's going on out there in
the world, which isn't always in our control,
is going to have less of an impact compared
to the immediate environment a child is in,
which we have much more control over. And that's
what would make a bigger difference in whether a
child grows up happy and resilient.
But if someone has thought about it and they
think it's an uphill battle and they're
not confident that they can provide the kind of
environment that would overcome all the s*** that's
going on out there, that's why they've decided
the most ethical thing for them to do is
to not have children, then fair enough.
They've thought it through and I think they made
a perfectly valid decision for themselves. But I
still wouldn't agree that bringing children into
this world in its current state is inherently
unethical or irresponsible. People who don't
experience parenthood are missing out on a
fundamental human experience. I would actually
agree. Although it depends on what it means by
fundamental human experience. But then again,
I feel like under most reasonable definitions,
raising children would be significant
and defining enough to qualify as a central human
experience. However, I'm not suggesting a person's
life will be incomplete or less fulfilling if they
don't have children. I don't think those are
the same things. You can miss out on a key
human experience and still find fulfillment, maybe
even more fulfillment somewhere else. Another way
I would think about it is, I believe most people
would say love is central to the human experience.
There are different forms of love, of course,
but the ones that immediately come to
mind are romantic love or family love and
of course the love that's unique to
a parent child relationship. But for example,
someone could have never fallen in love and we
might say they are missing out on that particular
aspect of the human experience. And even
then, they can definitely still live a complete and
fulfilling life. So at the end of the day,
if we didn't have children and someone said to me,
you're missing out on a fundamental human
experience, I wouldn't disagree. But that
wouldn't take anything away from the life that we
have lived. No one can experience everything life
has to offer. Some people want certain experiences
and some people don't. And that's it. Do I
want that experience? Actually, I do. But then
there's the question of whether I'm ready to be
a mother. I can be a pretty anxious person. So,
I like certainty. I would want everything
planned out and in perfect order before I could
feel ready to commit. But our lives are not
exactly conventional and parenthood is wildly
unpredictable. I realized the certainty I was
hoping for doesn't really exist. And
more than anything, I just really look forward to
experiencing parenthood together with my partner
who I've always thought would be a fantastic dad.
Now age is not on our side. The best time
to have kids has passed. The second best time
would be now. So earlier this year, we
thought, why not start trying? After all, things
might take a while or it might not happen at all.
But to our surprise, we didn't have to wait long.
And I'm extremely grateful and excited for that.
But I'll be lying if I said I didn't feel a sense
of anxiety kick in because of how quickly it all
happened. I'm just thankful that my child will
be in calm and safe hands even if I get
flustered along the way. Agree or disagree? I'm
ready to be a parent. I don't know if
I'll ever feel 100% ready to be a parent,
but I'm ready to adapt. This is going to be one
heck of an experience for sure. I'm going
to have to adapt and I can't wait.